Professor Ruth Pennybacker Collection
University of Houston Libraries
Professor Ruth Pennybacker Collection
1934-1981
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Pennybacker, Ruth
2.50 Linear Feet
The Ruth Pennybacker Collection consists of the teaching aids she used in class, photocopies of plays, news clippings, and programmes. Included in the collection is a scrapbook crafted in 1967 by her students, colleagues, and friends as a tribute to Miss Pennybacker.
1969-044
Biographical Note
Professor Ruth Pennybacker or "Miss Pennybacker", as she preferred, joined the U.H. faculty in 1935. Her application to the university included a letter of recommendation written by the distinguished Texas historian and writer J. Frank Dobie. Pennybacker, a 1934 Vassar graduate, went to work in the newly formed English Department at the University of Houston where she taught freshman composition and creative writing. A driving force in the creation of the U.H. creative writing program, Pennybacker also founded the Harvest, a campus publication for students, poets, and creative writers.
Scope and Contents
The Ruth Pennybacker Collection consists of the teaching aids she used in class, photocopies of plays, news clippings, and programmes. Included in the collection is a scrapbook crafted in 1967 by her students, colleagues, and friends as a tribute to Miss Pennybacker.
Forms part of the University Archives.
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
University of Houston; University of Houston. Creative Writing Program; University of Houston. Dept. of English
Genre/Form of Material:
Clippings; Correspondence; Scrapbooks; Scripts; Theater programs
Personal Name:
Barthelme, Donald; Pennybacker, Ruth
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Detailed Description
- Classroom Curriculum Material
  This series contains 24 folders, arranged alphabetically. The majority of these contain news clippings, correspondence and plays used as part of the classroom curriculum.
  - Article Clippings (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Brochures (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence To: Pennybacker (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence (Personal) To: Pennybacker (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Drama Notebook, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Drama Notebook, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Guest Book (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Personal Items (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Play: "A Separate Peace" (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Play: "Absent Friends" (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Play: "Betrayal - 1977" (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Play: "Black Cycle" (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Play: "Blinded by the Light" (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Play: "Breakfast Past Noon" (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Play: "Brontosaurus" (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Play: "Cabin 12" (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Play: "Evolution of People's Theatre" (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Play: "Firebugs" (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Play: "Freshwater" (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Play: "Good and Faithful Servant" (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Play: No Title (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Play: "Reunion" (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Play: "Three Women" (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Play: "Three Women" (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Play Readers Group Material
  This series contains 25 folders, arranged alphabetically. These folders consist of spiral notebooks and correspondence from the Play Readers group, organized chronologically from 1978 - 1981. Also contained in this series are poems, programmes and a copy of Pennybacker's 1934 thesis.
  - Play Readers (1of 2), 1970 - 1971 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Play Readers (2 of 2), 1970 - 1971 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Play Readers (1 of 2), 1972 - 1973 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Play Readers (2 of 2), 1972 - 1973 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Play Readers (1 of 2), 1973 - 1974 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Play Readers (2 of 2), 1973 - 1974 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Play Readers (1 of 2), April 1974 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Play Reader (2 of 2), April 1974 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Play Readers (1 of 2), 1974 - 1975 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Play Readers (2 of 2), 1974 - 1975 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Play Readers (1 of 2), 1975- 1976 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Play Readers (2 of 2), 1975 - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Play Readers (1 of 2), 1976 - 1977 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Play Readers (2 of 2), 1976 - 1977 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Play Readers (1 of 2), 1977 - 1978 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Play Readers (2 of 2), 1977 - 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Play Readers (1 of 2), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Play Readers (2 of 2), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Play Readers, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Play Readers, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Play Readers, No Date, Misc. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Poems by Gaye Doehring (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Programmes (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Programmes - The Austin Symphony Orchestra (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Programmes - Royal Shakespeare Company (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Thesis by Pennybacker (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Scrapbook, 1967
  This series contains a scrapbook dated 1967, that contains letters, notes and tributes to Miss Pennybacker. Included in the scrapbook are letters written by Joseph M. Doggett, Philip G. Hoffman, John C. Allred, John Q. Anderson, Vassar Miller, and Kenneth Carbajal.
  - Scrapbook: "Letters, Notes and Tributes - May 4, 1967" (Box 3, Item 1)